Finding aid for Manuel Luis Quezon papers, 1909-1944
Bentley Historical Library
Manuel Luis Quezon papers
1909-1944
Bentley Historical Library
Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944
852085 Aa 2
54 microfilms
President of the Commonwealth of the Philippines, 1935-1944; correspondence, memoranda, reports, speeches, articles, and other materials relating to his career, 1909-1944.
The microfilming of the papers of Manuel Quezon (donor no. 4715 ) was a joint project of the National Library of the Philippines and the University of Michigan. The agreement was signed in 1967 and the project completed in 1969.
The collection is open to research.
Manuel Luis Quezon (August 19, 1878-August 1, 1944) was born in Baler, Tayabas (now Quezon Province), Philippines. He was the eldest son of Lucio Quezon and Maria Dolores Molina; married Aurora Aragon, December 14, 1918; children, Maria Aurora, Maria Zeneida, and Manuel, Jr. Quezon was educated at the San Juan de Letrán College (B.A., summa cum laude, 1894) and University of Santo Tomás (Ll. B., 1903).
Provincial fiscal of Mindoro, 1903-1906; Municipal Concilor of Tayabas, Tayabas, 1906 (Resigned to run as governor of Tayabas Province, 1906); Co-founder of the Partido Independista Inmediata 1906-1907; Governor of Tayabas Province, 1906; First assemblyman from Tayabas to the First Philippine Assembly, 1907; Resident Commissioner of the Philippines to the United States, 1909-1917 (re-elected 1911, 1913, 1915); President of the Senate, 1916-1935; First President of the Commonwealth of the Philippines, 1935-1941; of the Commonwealth government-in-exile (Washington, D.C., U.S.A.), 1941-1944.
The Manuel Quezon microfilm was a joint project of the University of Michigan and the National Library of the Philippines. The resulting 54 reels of microfilm represent the most important, but not all, of the Quezon papers. The papers span the period beginning with Quezon's residence in Washington DC as Resident Commissioner and ending with his death in New York State during World War II. There is no material relating to his public service in Mindoro or Tayabas Province, approximately 1903-1909, or to his education.
The collection is of greatest importance for the wide range of Quezon's correspondence and for the documentation of the events and politics involved in the long history of the Philippine independence movement. Quezon corresponded widely both with political figures in the United States as well as with the other great leaders within the Philippines.
Due to the sensitivity of the positions he held, especially before independence, Quezon had cause to devise codes which he used in his correspondence. Staff members of the National Library have prepared a glossary of these words and numerical codes with their meaning. These code indices cover different chronological periods: Code I: 1911-1912; Code II: 1911 and January-July 1914; Code III: 1914-1915 (also known as the War Department code); Code IV: 1917-1929; Code V: 1930s. This code index has been place with the first set of microfilm boxes; a second set has been attached to the printed finding aid.
The collection has been arranged into three series: General Correspondence; Speeches, Articles, Statements, Reports, Interviews, and Book File; and Correspondents File.
Many of the documents had suffered physical damage or decay prior to microfilming. Some are fragments of the original and portions of others may be illegible due to staining, water damage or climate induced decay.
Lawyers -- Philippines.; Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.
- General Correspondence, 1909-1944; 21 reels
  General Correspondence (1909-1944; Reels 1-21) consists of letters, telegrams, cablegrams, radiograms, and memoranda sent and received. The papers have been arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by name of correspondent. The series divides into three chronological subseries corresponding to different phases or political responsibilities in Quezon's career. These subseries are: Resident Commissioner of the Philippines to the United States (1909-1916); President of the Senate (1916-1935); and President of the Commonwealth of the Philippines (1935-1944).
  For each subseries a brief, narrative scope and content note provides an overview Quezon's activities and the nature of the correspondence. For each roll, researcher Michael Cullinane has provided a more detailed list of significant topics and correspondents.
  - Resident Commissioner of the Philippines to the United States, 1909-1916
    The Resident Commissioner of the Philippines to the United States (1909-1916; Reels 1-7) subseries documents Quezon activities while serving in the United States. The papers are of two categories, his interaction with Americans on issues of Philippine independence and his communications with colleagues and other Philippine politicians on events taking place in Manila and elsewhere in the Islands. While serving in the United States, Quezon carried on extensive correspondence with Erwin Winslow and other members of the Anti-Imperialist League and with other individuals supportive of Philippine independence. The papers also indicate Quezon's efforts on behalf of Philippine modernization and economic prosperity as a necessary prerequisite to independence.
    - Nov. 9, 1909-August 5, 1911 (Reel 1)
      Highlights of roll 1, Nov. 9, 1909-August 5, 1911, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:
      Communications with individuals in the United States:
      Extensive correspondence with Erving Winslow (Secretary, Anti-Imperialist League) mostly re: working toward Philippine independence
      Correspondence with various U.S. congressmen, businesses, etc.
      Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines:
      Sergio Osmeña--extensive correspondence, mostly cablegrams, specifically:
      Osmeña to Quezon. Confidential letter in Spanish (Dec. 24, 1910)
      Quezon to Osmeña. Long letter (March 9, 1911)
      Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (April 21, 1911)
      Jaime de Veyra (kept Quezon informed of events in Manila)
      de Veyra to Quezon. Letter. Spanish (Dec. 7, 1910) re: Osmeña's work in Assembly
      de Veyra to Quezon. Letter. Spanish (Feb. 14, 1911)
      de Veyra to Quezon. Letter. Spanish (March 4, 1911)
      James Harbord--continual correspondence, usually personal and re: Philippine--American relations
      Harry Hill Bandholtz. Letter (March 23, 1910)
      Teodoro M. Kalaw--some confidential, informative letters to Quezon, especially
      letter (Aug. 2, 1911)
      Vicente Singson Encarnacion
      Singson to Quezon. 2 page letter (April 2, 1911)
      Quezon to Singson. 5 page reply (May 25, 1911)
    - August 5, 1911-July 19, 1912 (Reel 2)
      Highlights of roll 2, August 5, 1911-July 19, 1912, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:
      Extensive correspondence with Erving Winslow (Anti-Imperialist League)
      James Blount--occasional correspondence, especially
      James Blount to Quezon. Letter (May 6, 1912) re: his complaint of Quezon quoting from Blount's as yet unpublished manuscript on Philippine affairs under the U. S.
      James Blount to Quezon. Letter (May 8, 1912) much of same; later Quezon replies
      William A. Jones
      Various other U.S. congressmen mostly re: political status of the Philippines
      Sergio Osmeña--regular heavy correspondence, see especially
      Quezon to Osmeña. 7 page letter (Aug. 18, 1911). Quezon wants to stay in Washington longer since he's not needed in Philippines until next year to muster votes for party in election.
      Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (n.d., between late 1911 and early 1912)
      Osmeña to Quezon. 3 page letter (March 14, 1912)
      Quezon to Osmeña. 13 page letter (March 27, 1912) plus another related letter from the same time
      Quezon to Osmeña. 2 page letter (April 13, 1912)
      Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (June 8, 1912)
      Quezon to Osmeña. 2 page letter (June 14, 1912)
      Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (June 15, 1912)
      T. Pardo de Tavera (an occasional letter)
      Juan Villamor--interesting letter complaining of corruption in Manila
      T. Kalaw
      J. de Veyra--continual correspondence, especially interesting
      de Veyra to Quezon. 5 page letter (May 11, 1912)
      Quezon to de Veyra. Reply (June 20, 1912)
    - July 20, 1912-July 14, 1913 (Reel 3)
      Highlights of roll 3, July 20, 1912-July 14, 1913, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:
      Continuing correspondence with Erving Winslow
      James Blount
      Francis Woodruff
      Bishop C. Brent (mostly from Manila)
      Frank McIntyre (Chief, Bureau of Insular Affairs)
      Benito Legarda (Resident Commissioner, Washington)
      William M. Shuster (in Philippines and in U. S.). Much correspondence with him beginning in mid-1913 with Quezon maneuvering to have him appointed next Governor-General to follow Forbes.
      S. Osmeña--letters, cables, etc.--mostly concerning Philippine-U.S. relations, Philippine political maneuvering in Manila by Osmeña and by Quezon in Washington with respect to Philippine independence, some on Partido Nacioanalista, etc
      J. de Veyra
      T. Pardo de Tavera
      James Ross--regular friendly, mostly personal correspondence with occasional discussions of Philippine affairs and problems
      Newton W. Gilbert (Acting Governor-General)--official correspondence
      Other
      M. Kalaw's correspondence with Erwin Winslow, U.S. Congressmen, etc.--while Quezon was in Manila (late 1912 to early 1913)
    - July 21, 1913-June 29, 1914 (Reel 4)
      Highlights of roll 4, July 21, 1913-June 29, 1914, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:
      Correspondence with Erwin Winslow, also M. Kalaw's correspondence with Erwin Winslow in Quezon's absence
      Moorfield Storey--more frequent correspondence
      William Shuster--mostly re: effort to get him appointed Governor-General and his work as a lawyer for Renacimiento
      Frank McIntyre
      H. Parker Willis (Prof. in New York)
      Charles Miller (Editorial Staff, New York Times)--especially interesting:
      Quezon to Miller. Letters (March 19, 1914 and March 20, 1914) re: Quezon's defense of Philippine and refutation of Worcester, esp. his "Slavery" book (a big concern of Quezon)
      Numerous letters of other Americans (congressmen, businessmen, newsmen, etc.) to gain public and legislative support for Jones Bill
      V. Singson Encarnacion
      Two reports by Governor-General Forbes prior to his departure from Philippines re: state of peace throughout the Philippines--especially Aug. 25, 1913 report in which he expresses a concern that maybe Quezon is being given too big a hand in Philippine affairs and in Washington decision making
      Sergio Osmeña, heavy correspondence, especially interesting:
      Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (Aug. 26, 1913) re: Quezon's accompanying Harrison to Manila
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Aug. 30, 1913) re: his desire to have a Philippine Vice-Governor, and that all pro-Republicans would not agree to this
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Dec. 31, 1913) re: getting Shuster a commission appointment
      Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (Jan. 20, 1914)
      Quezon to Osmeña. 4 page letter (June 17, 1914) re: Jones Bill, and much other 1914 correspondence to get bill through U.S. Congress their way and in their form, attempt to expand legislative powers, create new powers for Philippines in all branches.
    - June 30, 1914-November 9, 1914 (Reel 5)
      Highlights of roll 5, June 30, 1914-November 9, 1914, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:
      Continuing correspondence with Erwin Winslow
      Moorfield Storey
      H. Parker Willis
      W. A. Jones
      W. M. Shuster
      Senator R. F. Pettigrew
      F. B. Harrison
      James Ross
      V. Singson Encarnacion, especially Quezon to Singson (Aug. 1, 1914) re: Quezon's explanation to him of his activities in Washington and fixing independence date
      F. Buencamino, Jr., especially his two letters to Quezon (Aug. 24, 28, 1914) re: his report to Quezon on the Manila situation upon his return there
      T. Kalaw, especially Kalaw to Quezon (Sept. 24, 1914) re: mostly Manila politics
      Assembly (Justo, Filemon and Lopez). Letter (Oct. 24, 1914) praising Quezon's good work for the Philippines
      Sergio Osmeña, especially correspondence dealing with Jones Bill, independence and Manila affairs
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (July 6, 1914) re: a mass meeting by the opposition parties in Manila
      Quezon to Mariano Lim, Sandiko and Sumulong. Letter drafts (July) 1914 re: his reactions to the meeting in Manila (noted above) expressing his criticism of their action
      Lim, Sandiko and Sumulong to Quezon. Cable (July 13, 1914) re: their explanation, saying they had not cabled him their desires because Quezon had already pursued the goal they sought, a specific date for independence to be in Jones Bill
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (July 14, 1914) re: introduction of Jones Bill to Congress, calming effect in Manila politics
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (July 15, 1914) expresses the pro-nationalism sentiment of pro-Jones U. S. Congress N.P. they say really represents people and N.P. will be main group responsible for implementing its politics
      Osmeña to Quezon. Letter 12 pages (Oct. 29, 1914) re: most Jones Bill
      Osmeña to Quezon. Letter 7 pages (Nov. 5, 1914) re: events and personalities in Manila
      Quezon to Osmeña. Letter 5 pages (Nov. 9, 1914)
      Osmeña to Quezon. Letter (Aug. 30, 1914) re: disagreement between Harrison and Riggs
      de Veyra
      de Veyra to Quezon. Letter (July 1, 1914)--notes about Denison (new Secretary of Interior): "es un Worcester en Reves"
      de Veyra to Quezon. 15 page letter (Sept. 10, 1914). He describes for Quezon's knowledge each of the new Democratic administrators in the Philippine Government: Harrison, Martin, Riggs, Denison
      de Veyra to Quezon. Letter (Sept. 16, 1914) re: more on Riggs, plus a resolution by the "Junta Recaudadora..."
      de Veyra to Quezon. 13 page letter (Sept. 21, 1914) re: Manila affairs
    - November 11, 1914-March 25, 1916 (Reel 6)
      Highlights of roll 6, November 11, 1914-March 25, 1916, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:
      Erwin Winslow
      James Blount--who offers to make replies to Worcester's accusation, Quezon tells him he will do it himself
      Woodrow Wilson
      Numerous U.S. congressmen re. Jones Bill
      Secretary Denison
      Lope K. Santos (especially Feb. 22, 1916)
      V. Singson Encarnacion (especially Jan. 20, 1915) re: Jones Bill
      T. Pardo de Tavera, especially letter, Quezon to Pardo de Tavera, Nov. 10, 1915, where Quezon notes: "Yo estoy convencido que [Worcester] es un hombre que tiene muy poco respecto a ca verdad."
      Sergio Osmeña (heavy correspondence), particularly:
      Quezon to Osmeña. 7 page letter (Nov. 11, 1914)
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Dec. 8, 1914) re: Sixto Lopez affair and notes: "Coming from certain towns Bulacan, I think Nac. Party are now in control there." [Sandiko's Prov] - Quezon replies to this letter, Dec. 11, 1914
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Dec. 11, 1914)--notes that they are keeping Secretary Denison quiet during sensitive debate on Jones Bill in Washington
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Dec. 15. 1914) re: their strong mutual loyalty and Harrison
      Quezon to Osmeña. 5 page letter (Dec. 18, 1914) thanks Osmeña for his praise, and praises Osmeña in turn
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Dec. 19, 1914)--suggests redistributing Senate districts, speaks of balancing off provinces with others politically
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Dec. 21, 1914)--suggests no need to redistrict, too difficult
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Jan. 4, 1915) re: "uprising" Navotas, Rizal and incapable government of Rizal
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Jan. 4, 1915)--suggesting that if Gov. Rizal is incompetent, he should have him removed
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 8, 1915) re: military intervention (esp. Harrison's failure to act)
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Feb. 8, 1915) re: how to handle above situation
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 23, 1915)--above satisfactorily handled by Harrison
      Heavy correspondence re: Clarke amendment May 1915-Feb. 1916 Osmeña wants Phil. Assembly's independence bill with date to be considered before Clarke amendment, in Jan. 1916, Phil. Assembly finally endorses Clarke amendment
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Jan. 26, 1916) re: Sandiko's effort to get together with Sen. Clarke and Democratic party in Washington
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Jan. 28, 1916) "Sandiko Party are claiming Clarke amendment as their own"
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Jan. 28, 1916) re: his proof that Clarke amendment was his baby, and he works with Clarke on it
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Jan. 30, 1916) Reports that Sandiko meeting celebrating their pretended victory because of the Clarke amendment was held this morning without any consequence
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 5, 1916) re: another opposition meeting and resolution
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Feb. 5, 1916) calm among opposition
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 8, 1916) re: conservative Philippine opinion of Clarke amendment, also re: Sandiko and Sumulong activities
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 11, 1916) re: some opposition guarantees to moderate their behavior
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 13, 1916) "...nobody knows here the inside of the Jones Bill situation. The information is not necessary but may be convenient and will use it as circumstances warrant." [re: earlier Quezon to Osmeña cable on Jones]
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Feb. 15, 1916) "...I think would be good idea to have Singson and Sandiko recommend neutralization..."
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 25, 1916) re: inability to get local resolutions, etc. in support of Clarke amendments, suggests that Sandiko's pro-Clarke activities may have deterred many from endorsing the amendment
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable from Cebu (March 7, 1916) "There are some movements among the progresistas in Iloilo against Clarke amendment..." [but Osmeña notes that Nacionalistas there held a "mass meeting" in support of the amendment]
    - March 25, 1916-October 15, 1916 (Reel 7)
      Highlights of roll 7 (part), March 25, 1916-October 15, 1916, with notes and comments by Michael Culliane:
      W. M. Shuster (now returned to U.S.)
      James Long
      James Ross (now in U.S.)
      Mr. Stone re: building sugar mills in Negros
      Harold M. Pitt (President, Manila Merchants' Association)
      Vincente Sotto, esp: Quezon to Sotto. Letter [in response to a letter from Sotto accusing Quezon of making contradicting statements]--Quezon defends himself, stresses that any seeming contradictions are changes in form, not content
      de Veyra to Quezon, some letters concern "grave crisis" facing hemp
      Sergio Osmeña (heavy correspondence):
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (March 29, 1916)--inquiring as to truth of rumors about wealthy in Iloilo being opposed to Clarke amendment in newspaper
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (March 30, 1916) "...there is no truth in report published and Harrison cabled accordingly, statement will be given out tomorrow after fresh information from Iloilo, Occid. Neg secured."
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (April 11, 1916) quotes endorsement of Clarke amendment by people of Iloilo and Negros Occidental
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (April 22, 1916) re: above (Iloilo)
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (April 27, 1916) long note clearing up above affair
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (May 2, 1916) re: defeat of Clarke amendment in Congress
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (July 17, 1916) re: suggested new political leaders
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (July 17, 1916) re: his desire to offer government positions to Justo Lukew and Gregorio Nieva [presumably for faithful party service]
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (October 4, 1916) re: congratulations for "grandiose" Nacionalista victory led by Osmeña
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (June 13, 1917) re: Worcester and Visayas Refining Co.
  - President of the Senate
    The President of the Senate (1916-1935; Reels 7-18) subseries details the evolution of the Philippine government with the filling of positions by Philippine nationals and his increasingly difficult relationship with speaker of the Philippine Assembly Sergio Osmeña for control of the legislature and the Nacionalista party. There is continuing documentation of the relationship between the Philippines and the United States with the drafting of legislation in the United States leading to independence, first the Hare-Hawes-Cutting Act (which was reject by the Philippine legislature), then the Tydings-McDuffie Act which passed.
    - October 16, 1916-February 15, 1918 (Reel 7)
      Highlights of roll 7, October 16, 1916-February 15, 1918, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (June 18, 1917) re. Worcester and Visayas Refining Co.
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (August 7, 1917)--more of Worcester and Visayas Refining Co., plus he expresses dissatisfaction with Nieva' s review
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (August 8, 1917) "...referring to Nieva, I think very important we have our own printing plant, that could publish newspaper and magazine. If you approve idea I shall buy press and linotypes. Yangco and Fernandez can fix it."
    - February 21, 1918-April 1, 1919 (Reel 8)
      Highlights of roll 8, February 21, 1918-April 1, 1919, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:
      Erwin Winslow--much less now with Quezon in Philippines
      F. McIntyre
      Charles M. Yeater
      General Walcutt
      Rafferty (San Francisco)
      J. de Veyra and Yangco (Resident Commissioners.) - extensive correspondence, especially with de Veyra re: business (i.e. hemp prices, setting up business in Philippines, etc.), some also relate to integration of Philippine National Guard into U.S. Federal Service
      V. Madrigal (Madrigal and Co., Manila) mostly re: building up sugar industry, includes charts, etc. (late 1918)
      C. A. Fernandez (Negros)--re: sugar centrals in Bais, Tanjay, LaCarlota--some details concerning town and their haciendas (esp. September 28, 1918)
      "Confidential memorandum for Governor-General" by Osmeña and Quezon (November 19, 1918)--mostly re: business and agriculture in Philippines.
      Sergo Osmeña (much correspondence):
      Osmeña to Quezon. Letter (Feb. 21, 1918) re: a commemoration for deceased Antonio
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (May 19, 1918) re: acquiring competing coconut industry in Cebu
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (June 17, 1918) N.P.'s nominating procedure
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (June 21, 1918)--gives his o.k.
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable [rush to Cebu] (Sept.9, 1918) re: sadness in Osmeña family
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Sept. 10, 1918) re: Osmeña reply to Quezon sympathy
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Sept. 19, 1918) re: Singson's "turncoating"
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Sept. 24, 1918) re: his reply to above Osmeña to Quezon.
      Cable to Washington (Feb. 3, 1919) "Minority party is endeavoring to have legislation pass a repel asking the U.S. and allied powers to grant Philippines a seat at the peace conference. Please cable at once what we can say and what we cannot say on this matter."
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Feb. 4, 1919) re:"..Harrison is as strong as ever with U.S..."
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 5, 1919) re: his help of D. Jakosauen
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (March 26, 1919) re: cutting size of independence mission and at same time trying to avoid the cropping up of "jealousies, envies and resentments of members..."